this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet se radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software
[Music]
hey this is Jeremy Jung for software
engineering radio today I'm speaking
with Sumeet Kumar Sumita is the head of
engineering at share now which is
previously car2go he's also the creator
of an open-source plugin called leaflet
geo man which provides drawing tools for
the leaflet mapping library I'll be
speaking with Sumeet about his
experience working with leaflet and how
developers can build mapping
applications with it so Sumeet welcome
to software engineering radio hello
thanks for having me so the first thing
I'd like to start with is for people who
aren't familiar with leaflet what is it
and what types of projects would people
build with it so leaflet is basically a
mapping library a JavaScript library for
mobile friendly interactive maps that's
how they say it and basically if you
want a map and you don't want to use
Google Maps for example for whatever
reason leaflet is basically an open
source alternative to to Google Maps and
other mapping providers of course you
still need map itself so basically the
images of of a map where you can have
open street map or any other provider
but with leaflet you can if I would have
to describe it you basically create the
layers on top of the map so that means
polygons markers points of interest to
show any data that you might have and to
zoom around the map and stuff like this
so it's it's the library around the map
itself and gives developers really
really good tools to do their own
mapping solutions and you're mentioning
if you didn't want to use Google Maps
for whatever reason I'm sure a lot of
people are familiar with Google Maps
what are kind of some of the main
reasons you might not choose it so in
big corporations for example
a lot of companies don't want to be tied
in so there are licensing reasons there
are especially in Germany or in Europe
there are data protection reasons there
is simply a stigma attached to Google in
that sense then there are Google uses a
custom format for their geo data and
leaflets you can use with an open
standard called geo JSON you can use it
if Google - as far as I know but it's
it's basically will transform everything
to the Google proprietary format and of
course it's much more expensive that is
also reason especially for startups or
individual developers with side projects
if they have a big volume if they expect
bigger traffic then Google Maps is quite
expensive hmm and you were talking about
how even though leaflet exists to kind
of provide maps you still need a source
for those maps so what are some examples
of sources people would use yeah that's
a good question so normally people use
Open Street Map which is free to use but
I'm being quite honest I think the
Google Street Map maps are not very
pretty so all the projects that I do
even if it's open source I use map box
in that sense that box is a company that
I would say is built on top of leaflet I
think last time I checked even the
maintainer sort of core maintenance of
leaflet work at map box so the company
grew out of leaflet from my
understanding and it's highly compatible
with leaflet and they provide beautiful
maps this is not free so I pay myself
for great maps in the background to use
even for my open source projects but you
can use basically any provider you want
so there is also here Maps it's a
European provider there is Google Maps
of course you can use that I'm not
entirely sure about Apple Maps if you
can use that with leaflet but any
provider where you have where you can
fetch the tiles as what it's called you
can implement it in to leaflet and
leaflet is a mapping tool that means
it's not about only about like satellite
maps or street maps you can also use
indoor maps you can use a map of the
Moon or Mars
you can use maps of video games or Game
of Thrones like it doesn't matter at the
end so any image that you that you can
take from an area can be a map and this
could be even a photo or a
blue what what's it called in English
you know a map of your house you could
even use that as a digital map and
create whatever you need on top of it
mm-hmm and in that case would it be like
you just have a JPEG or like you know a
static image and then you kind of
reference that so someone's able to to
click around that so I've never done a
tile a on myself honestly so but I've
seen an application build with with the
library that I I maintain and this is a
SAS application for construction sites
so they fly a drone on top of the
construction site take some HD photo of
it or even if okay I'm not entirely sure
and then they create a map out of it
that they then draw on top of on the
construction site which is really
interesting and as far as I know it's
it's quite easy for them to to make a
tile layer out of it the biggest
problem with a tile layer is always
zooming in and out of the map so you
need different
distances basically and of course the
file size so if you do an HD photo and
you open the map and it has to load
multiple HD photos this creates quite
some load and a slow for the user so
this optimization is the hardest part
but other than that if you research how
to how to do that I am pretty sure there
are tools for that that make it quite
easy and when you talk about
tiles for a map is it where you're
starting with like a really high
resolution image and then you're you're
cutting it into a bunch of pieces so
that as the person zooms around the map
there they're not having to load that
entire image it's optimized for exactly
this so it loads as many tiles that are
visible on screen so if you zoom in then
it only only loads the tiles that are
visibilities are usually I would say six
images or so and they should be quite
quite optimized in size if you have a
huge image with that that covers a big
area if you zoom out then instead of
loading 1000 tiles you load only six
tiles that show simply more more area
but in less detail so the the load for
the user is basically always the same
doesn't matter which which zoom level
and you start with a high-resolution
image and then cut it down mm-hmm but
again I've never done it myself so not a
hundred percent sure on that sure when
people talk about map sources sometimes
they talk about raster tiles and
sometimes they talk about vector data
what's kind of the main difference
between the two and when would you use
each a vector data itself you can think
if your frontal developer you can think
of it like an SVG so it's an image
versus an SVG an image has a fixed
dimension with and hate and if you zoom
in the quality gets lower okay so the
quality gets gets lower a bit if you
zoom in and
with an SVG it's kind of rendered by the
browser so it has infinite scalability
in in a sense and with vector maps it's
kind of the same I'm not sure if there
is a bit of a stretch to mapping experts
but the good thing for me if I use
vector maps you can zoom in and out very
fluently they are oftentimes not
particular steps to the next image but
it's a smooth transition and especially
if you use something like canvas mode
and leaflet it's it's a it's a much
smoother experience for the user but
these are not individual images anymore
so I'm not talking necessarily about the
tiles right now but about the layers you
put on top so let's say you have markers
of Tesla supercharger
for example and you put them on the map
these can be individual Dom elements and
if you have 6,000 of them it creates a
lot of load for the for the browser but
if you have something like canvas mode
its drawn inside one element and
everything is smooth and performant
again you have the downside of you
cannot interact with the Dom elements
individually of course but I might
getting a bit out of out of your
question right now because
Vectron Maps itself can be if you refer
to tiles there might be even some
additional advantages that that are not
sure yet what I do know is that uber for
example created their own library also
on top of open source products I think
it was on top of map box and they use
only only vector tiles like this because
they have huge data needs and they need
very performant Maps and if you use
leaflet only like just out of the box
how it's coming and you have big big big
data then you might get into performance
problems problems that I have myself but
not yet solved in particular apps that I
built hmm and when you're talking about
like these big sets of data is this like
the mapping data in terms of things like
you know streets and locations or is
this more of overlaid on top of that
that's definitely overlays on top of
that so I can do some examples I as you
as I said I'm working in the mobility
sector or car sharing company
that's also how I got into leaflets six
seven years ago because they needed a
geo spatial data management tool
basically that I have built and
the data that they use are you know
points of interests electric charging
stations we have parking zones drop
zones for the cars we separate the the
city into polygons to track demand in
specific areas of course and then you
have other companies like mask which is
a logistics company they have zones
where their ships drive and stop off the
harbours it's
you have Tesla for example has that
supercharger stations which is small
data compared to that and
ridiculously detailed data like if we
are talking autonomous vehicles then you
need data like you know you separate the
road into different lanes for example
one goes in one direction the other one
in the other direction you have parking
spots in this for a whole city or a
whole country this is data that is so
big and so much your browser will just
crash if you try to display it and leave
it alone and so to start like it's a
very simplest case if someone is trying
to put on a list of parking locations or
superchargers things like that what does
the API look like that for leaflet are
people calling functions that are adding
these one by one or is it sinking to a
collection like what does that look like
so then which of your options in leaflet
which is quite cool so normally what I
do is I try to use the data always in
Geo Jason so I store it maybe in a
different format but in general in my 8
the API is I built around leaflet use
trio Jason normally and leaflet you can
add geo jason simply so there is a geo
Jason method where you just put in the
data and it displays it on the map you
can also create your own shapes that
means a circle marker a circle polygon a
line you know a marker all these kind of
functions they have then you basically
give it to coordinates and it creates
the shape on the map with Geo Jason it's
kind of a wrapper for everything so if
you provided geo Jason it can be markers
can be polygons can be lines and the
leaflet will just add everything it
depends on your needs or your source of
data that you have and particularly with
my library where I create the shapes so
the user can draw the shapes in him or
herself I need all of those functions
basically and you were saying that geo
Jason
is a good option for kind of storing the
locations of different things storing
shapes and things like that how about
for data that kind of changes often like
you were saying if you have a car
sharing application you might have live
locations of where cars are just as an
example with geo Jason be suitable for
something like that so I'm sure there
are people that disagree with me I had
discussions actually with developers
from uber and also some let's say
mapping experts from from other
companies and the opinions vary I can
only speak for myself even though Jason
or JJ's mod might not be the most
efficient storing format out there it's
basically a standard in in in modern
api's to use Jason or geo Jason as as
the formats to exchange data and I like
to have not a lot of
transformations with my data so I store
it as much as I can in GU Jason it works
fine for me I don't have any
restrictions or downsides for that
currently granted I don't build
applications on the scale of uber but
uber also told me they they store it in
GU traces they don't have a problem with
it either they like to use open
standards and I agree with that and if
we are talking live data it doesn't
matter how how frequent the location for
example of a marker is updated let's say
every half a second you update the
location of a moving car you simply
store the true coordinates into it and
you can build it as a you store the
entirety of Jason again or you store
only the change coordinate really the
subset of the actual data it doesn't
matter how you build it it's so small in
comparison that it will only make a
difference if you have I don't know if
you update a thousand or a million
entries all at the same time then of
course your network is gonna slow down a
little bit but this has nothing really
to do with geo chase no trace and this
is any data if you have so much data
updates you should look at something
like a message queue like RabbitMQ or
Kufner or something like this but if
you're doing interest over REST API I
would personally batch batch the request
so every second or every two seconds I
would update all the entries that have
been changed if we're talking about a
front-end or something and batch
everything together so to make sure I
understand correctly if you were getting
the locations of cars and you query the
backend API you would get a geo JSON
file which is just basically just a
regular JSON file that has a bunch of
elements that might have say the
latitude and longitude of each car and
as you got updates like you were saying
like maybe you get an update every
second or every few seconds you would
receive new geo JSON files from the
server and it would just have the
elements that had changed or new
elements so there are two different
points in and let's say an application
stack where you have these updates the
first one is the car sends an update to
your back-end and if we are talking
about our company for example Chanel or
companies that use my open-source
product this might be for example
10,000 cars always connected to some
sort of back-end and they send their
location maybe every second for example
let's say you have a network hiccup and
they all reconnect at the same time you
have a huge spike because 10,000 cars
and the location at once and this is an
area where you where we at least make
the experience don't use just HTTP using
a user message queue and so we can
handle all of the data because the cars
do not only send a location they also
send is the window down is it up motor
start motorists stopped event so
everything that happens in a car
connected car is sent to a server and
this can be multiple events per second
if we're talking ten thousand a hundred
thousand Vee
or scooters or whatever it is this load
should be handled by a message queue
like Kafka or rabbitmq once it's in the
backend and you just want just in
quotation marks want to display it on a
front end then we we are talking a
different story here because a front end
doesn't have a message queue like this
we can use if you want to do it really
in a real-time sense you can use
WebSockets which is yeah you send
incremental updates as they come in to
the front end and change your data and
this can be just basically an ID and a
new latitude and longitude and you
connect the data in the front end it can
be a new Jason it's completely dependent
on how you build it I normally send some
metadata with Jason that is for example
a name of the license plate the name of
the car maybe the model you know is this
a Mercedes or a BMW or whatever and
maybe even some other data depending on
the project depending on the data that
you get there is maybe a lot of metadata
involved then I don't send the entire
Jason then I just sent a
updated information but if you are not
using a WebSocket if you're using HTTP
then there is no push from the server
the browser has to fetch updated
information so in this case what I would
do is let's say I display the live on a
map and we have I'm just taking as an
example share now and car2go here of
course can be applied to any company out
there if we are talking 2,000 cars for
example and I want to show them in real
time I will simply fetch the list of all
cars every second or every two seconds
so there is no push or anything I will
just do a fetch a
simple interval request and so you're
doing this this fetch on this interval
and is it taking into account what it
chooses to display it's just taking that
entire document and showing everything
that you're sending or is it performing
some kind of a comparing the elements
you already had and the new elements
yeah yeah that's a good question so I do
it if but it depends on the project so
I'm building a little SAS product around
mapping probe yeah geo management
basically and there are you stiffs out
of yeah I did a mistake of not not
diffing and the reason is if you if you
redraw the layers on a map it's a lot of
performance overhead and if you do this
every second and
currently you are maybe creating another
layer on the map you are interacting
with them up in some other way this this
is a performance problem also the map
constantly rearend us basically your
data and
then the map simply gets laggy right and
if you want to do anything else on the
map it gets sluggy and it's not a good
performance so I use tipping that if out
of 2,000 cars only to move then they
will get updated and the rest is just
thrown away mm-hmm and internally so
when you're talking about using this
death does that mean on the leaflet side
or on the JavaScript side you have this
geo JSON document and then you're
updating that geo JSON document and
leaflet just figures out that you know
only those two elements changed and it
doesn't touch the rest of the page yeah
that would be great but sadly as far as
I know it's not it's not like that so
you give leaflet something to draw and
they withdraw it so I do the diff
basically on the business application
side on the business logic side I do
this myself I'm doing when I get the
payload basically to the to the payload
that is already there with standard I
guess low - do it do a comparison remove
everything else and then I have to
remove the layers first that are
currently in in leaflet and then I fit
in the new ones and I also have my own
IDs associated with everything so I can
you know compare also individual shapes
on the map or layers on the map leaflet
it has itself also IDs that they create
when you add something to the net but I
they are not consistent so if you put if
you add a marker to the map it has an ID
if you want to add the same marker to
the map again with a different location
it gets a different ID you can get the
current one on the map and update that
one that is also possible but then you
would have to buy in completely in to
the leaflet logic including their IDs
and how to handle everything and I like
to have this separate I like to have
leaflet just as a let's say as a dumb
drawing tool and not as the source of
truth for my IDs and IDs and business
logic and all of that so I do this
outside I do the diffing outside I do
the storing to the database outside and
leave it is just like a component I feed
it data it draws it and that's that's
about it mmm so in the case of
situations where you have live data and
you have a lot of data changing it
sounds like you actually aren't using
geo Jason in that case you're actually
you have your own collection outside of
leaflet and you're using that along with
your own dipping to determine which
elements you should find inside of
leaflet based off of a key and then
moving just the ones that you found that
have changed no so that's actually it's
it's true Jason it's all GU Jason that I
store if I for example to assess who
that I build has an API where you can
fetch the layers that are displayed on
the map and from an API and this is all
GU Jason and internally I only use to
you Jason and that means so if you put
it into leaflet internally in leaflet
it's also transformed to something else
of course but the map you can just say
okay give me these layers and make them
GU Jason basically and then this is how
my whole application uses it but GU
Jason has a
properties block and in there you can
add all the metadata you want so in
there I have two IDs that that are
basically the reference to my database
in there I have maybe a
gravitational center of a specific
polygon for example I have descriptions
names anything the user would like to
see I store in the properties property
of true Jason
and use that everywhere so it's still
all Geo Jason mmm you have let's say a
single geo JSON document for all of your
car locations and if you go inside that
geo Jason find the key of a car that you
want to move you can update the
location through the Jade Jason and so
yeah that's actually a pretty good
question and this depends a bit on the
application that that you're building so
do Jason allows you to group layers
together that means if you have one
polygon cool you can have that if you
have two or three or a hundred you can
group them in what's called a feature
collection and
you can store it this way that's
completely fine then you have big
payloads but you have to get into the
geo Jason and like get the specifics out
of it in the SAS application I have this
use case to count and limit the layers
that a user can draw on a map and this
means I want this to be separate
database entries so I can a user can
also choose to share one layer versus
the other with the public or with a
colleague or whatever and to have this
granular permission system kind of I
need this to be separate database
entries and that means each layer on the
map is for me personally a different geo
JSON but again this this is highly
customized to my use case I am sure
there are users out there for example if
they fetch my data from geo Jason
through the API they would not like to
have a thousand different geo Jason's in
an array for or a collection for all the
markers they would just like to have one
big geo jason file that that owns all of
the data this is easy to do like you can
just combine them that's that's that's
fine and I will do this on the API level
but for my use case I store them
separately mmm okay so when we're
talking about geo Jason in a lot of
cases you actually choose to have a
separate geo JSON document for each mark
koror each thing that you're gonna put
onto the map exactly okay cool so we
were kind of talking about how you know
you're bringing in data on the back end
and then you're bringing it in as geo
Jason on the front end is the geo Jason
is that something that you're converting
at the API level or are you actually
storing your data as geo Jason on the
backend as well so yeah this is the
embarrassing part of the application
especially when you
yeah when you start out and I mean I've
I'm building this application for a long
time but there is tech depth of course
and that is one thing so what got me up
fast I use firebase as a data storage or
fire store it's called and this just
helps me to to simply you know ramp up
an application quite fast and I still
use it even after a month many months I
think a year now that I'm building this
application and in there you have a
limitation of how you the documents how
you store it the document format is
limited so I cannot have nested arrays
but geo jason has quite a lot of nested
errors especially if you have multi
polygons that means multiple polygons
belonging to one layer acting as one
layer basically with holes in it for
example this is some multiple levels of
nested arrays you can just store this in
fire store you have to store it as a
JSON string so basically what does me
what this means is I store my dress and
as I strength currently that means on a
database level I can't do any queries
anything I do with the data I first
fetch it with the cloud functions or a
node node script or whatever I fetch the
data first then I do the calculations on
top of it for example is a point inside
this geo JSON or is are these
polygons near the user or whatever I do
all the calculations and then I I serve
the data SGO jason of course so I store
it as GU Jason in a sense but it's a
string
and if I would have to do it again or if
I look into the roadmap for the future I
would probably go to something like
MongoDB where you can I'm not sure if
it's like native to you Jason support
but the important part is that if you
build an application that basically does
a lot of of geo queries and stuff like
this if it's made to handle give special
data use an database that can do your
queries on a database level that means I
give I give the database a coordinate
like whatever my location and
and do a query like give me all
polygons that where this point is inside
the polygon this is something if you can
do this on a database level this adds a
lot of performance because otherwise if
we're talking thousands or millions of
layers you have to fetch everything and
calculate this on your back-end on the
backend side and this is expensive so I
would go to to a database that allows
geo queries firebase says they have this
they have this in a very very limited
format I asked this on Stack Overflow I
saw the question yesterday again I asked
us about two years ago
2016 and back then they answer that they
haven't exposed their geo queries yet
and they still happened so I'm not sure
when they come out with it but if I need
it I would switch databases I will not
wait for that and if I would start over
I would choose the database beforehand
that that allows me to do that mm-hmm
and for your work at share now how are
you storing the the geo data there I
have not touched that particular product
in quite a while but back then when we
built it it was trio tracin but we
stored we used MongoDB and I'm not
entirely sure if you can simply without
any transformation store geo Dresden
MongoDB but MongoDB has G okras so I
know I know that much but I can tell you
right now on out of the top of my head
if you have to transform it or if
MongoDB for example that's true Jason
but trans transforms it internally that
I don't know and you know we're kind of
talking about how you can have an
application with a lot of data but
depending on where the user is looking
on the map they don't necessarily need
to bring in all that data at once what
are kind of the strategies used to deal
with that that is a good one so what do
queries often allow you to do is if I
look on a map you can define the borders
by basically the top left top right
bottom left bottom right corners of your
screen so if I have a map on my screen I
can say our leaflet and any mapping
library can basically give you the
boundaries that you are currently
looking at and these are these four
coordinates and if your database
supports geo queries you can basically
say give me all layers that that are
inside this piece boundaries and then
you can just fetch that data this is how
I would do it from the top of my hat
honestly I've not built it like this
because I have not had to deal with
those big kind of data sets and
there might be downsides to this if the
user for example moves the map how many
how many queries do you do then you know
you have a moving target basically but
I'm sure there are ways to solve this so
this this would be my first clue on how
to achieve this mm-hm and in terms of
when you're working on a leaflet
application do you have any experience
integrating a leaflet map with other
frameworks like say react or view or
something like that very good question I
get this quite often on the open source
library as well and
with with mapping libraries like leaflet
you are basically back to to the roots
of HTML and JavaScript where you
interact with the Dom elements directly
and with the introduction of frameworks
like angular and react a now view we
kind of moved past us like that these
are all abstractions to the Dom element
we don't we don't say create these diff
and create this diff we don't do this
anymore
but with
leaflets you still at least a little bit
have to do this in the sense that for
example you tell it that if that it
should render in and you call
specific elements directly sometimes
through the leaflet API of course but
it's it doesn't have this reactive
nature like our frameworks today do so
what happens is that there are a lot of
abstractions to mapping libraries so
there is leaflet react or react leaflet
view leaflet all these abstractions to
use the mapping library in the same
reactive way in the same thinking mode
of the framework which which is good for
anyone that is starting out I personally
like to use it bare-bones so I like to
interact with leaflet directly with with
API it provides I have full control over
it maybe I'm an advanced user in a sense
could be but the abstractions that are
out there they limit me because I always
have to go through that I always if
there is a new feature or an edge case I
want to tackle or something I always
need the buy-in of the maintainer of
that abstraction and this is something I
I don't do or sometimes I build my own
abstraction but normally I basically
build a component in view and it doesn't
matter if it's react or angular view I
build a component that owns the map
itself and I put as a property I put the
Geo jason in there for example and the
component the solder all the rests may
be the dipping even the rendering the
updating the watching of the properties
but you have to build your watch trust
yourself and and stuff like this so it's
just out of context normally and just
yeah not every developer is comfortable
with this especially if you start
programming and you start in the world
with react in the world of react so
you're not used to this bare bone coding
but if you if you use other libraries
that are that are interacting with the
Dom elements directly then it helps you
know it's a good exercise to to connect
these two worlds another another use
case might be where you could use your
skill sets in the sense our charting
libraries so if you if you display
charts for example on a dashboard it's
the same same topic there so basically
like you recommend keeping your
framework code basically separate from
your interactions with leaflet like
you'll use leaflets built in api's not
use a wrapper just because you want to
make sure you have full control and not
be limited exactly and if there is a new
you know a new version of leaflet coming
out I want to use it immediately it's
probably have some some updates that I
want to want to put in and again I like
I have to feeling I can control the user
experience much much better if I can
interact with leaflet directly through
the api's so it's not I wouldn't
necessarily say I would recommend it
it's the way how I do it and I think you
have if you build an advanced the big
application I think you're better off
using the leaflet api's directly if you
just want to display a map and maybe a
mark on top of it for example to show
the location of your business on your
business website then it's totally fine
to use a wrapper right that's that's
easy you will have it done in less than
an hour and that's it but if you build a
big application to handle geospatial
data then it's a different story and
there I would say remove the obstruction
and go directly with the library and for
these components that are from you know
your framework do those end up rendering
kind of surrounding the map like you
would have a side bar or a top bar or
something like that yeah also also a
good question so on Geo Men I use it so
this this SAS product is also the demo
website basically for them for the open
source library and it's called geo man
and there I have a map component as I
said and it's basically full screen from
the Dom side of course I have stuff
around it after I have a sidebar in a
sense and a footer and whatnot but we've
CSS you know I just displayed
differently so and the map is for me
always front and center it's the biggest
element and it should be basically like
Google Maps it should be the one big
background thing and the header and the
sidebar just like on top of the map and
you can build it in in different ways
like you could even add this to leaflet
if you would do everything in leaflet
you could even add your sidebar as a map
element on the map and just but I don't
do this I have the map container and I
just overlay my my other Dom elements on
top of the map so I want to keep this
really separate to mean the map itself
the map component is definitely one
separate component for me that I that I
interact with
because of login again let's say I want
to change mapping providers at one point
instead of changing one component I
would have to change that I don't know
the whole application so I try to keep
this as separate as possible so you
basically if you were to look at the
HTML the the Dom nodes that have kind of
all your controls or your sidebars
things like that they would be
completely independent the leaflet Dom
node but you use CSS maybe with like a
fixed position or something to appear on
top of the map is that correct yeah
that's that's true I would do one
exception though I an open source
library as you mentioned for drawing
basically layers on the map markers
lines whatever these buttons they I add
them to leaflet so because it's a
leaflet plugin so that means any user of
leaflet that wants to use my plugin just
imports it and it adds these buttons to
the leaflet map so there I
use the leaflet framework to display
this but anything else like for example
an address search the list of the layers
that is currently on there an export
button for downloading the geo Jason
changing the tires from Street View to
satellite you this kind of stuff you can
all add to the map and a lot of people
do that but I personally keep this out
of out of the map I have to separately
again because I in my SAS application I
would like to have more control over the
user experience and maybe you know I
have something like a paywall in front
of it or an upsell button or I need to
limit this based on user permissions and
I simply feel more comfortable doing
this in the framework like view instead
of leaflet itself mm-hmm and you know
you were talking about how you you built
a plug-in can you sort of talk a little
bit about what sort of things make sense
to be built as plugins vs. built outside
of them yeah also a very good question I
thought of that as well
sometimes my thoughts went to you know
if you have a like just stuff I just
mentioned an edge research and a list of
layers and stuff like this I thought
about him what if everything of that is
a plugin for leaflet I could open source
everything I just add everything modular
to leaflet could be a way again this is
then very like it's a big login of
course into the leaflet ecosystem so
this is all possible and there are
plugins I think for for all of that
there are plugins for your for your
address search their plugins to switch
tiles
plugins to draw to export data for all
of that there are plugins already and
they add this to the leaflet map again I
think if you have a use case of just
having a small map showing some small
stuff or you want to create an MVP it's
completely an MVP meaning a small app
that can do something where yeah it's
not a product that you might sell to
someone you can do all of that and it's
it will be completely sufficient and
it's probably less work to just use a
plugin to add this to the map but if you
have a product and you know you want to
create you want to control the design
aspects of it a lot and maybe animations
and stuff like this I think for every
developer it's more convenient to not
fiddle in leaflet code for that leaflet
has its own CSS also so you have to
override this or compete with it over
over the styles sometimes here and there
and
keeping it out of it just means the data
that is displayed and so between these
components has to flow through somewhere
and if you build a big application you
probably have an application state state
somewhere like in react what is it
called redux for example redux know
where you where you have your data store
on the front end and if you use this as
your source of truth you can use it for
all the components that you display on
top of the map that are not inside
leaflet and it's much easier using that
ecosystem then recreating everything in
leaflet because if you do that you
basically don't need a framework anymore
you build everything in in the leaflet
library and you interact with the Dom
again directly so the abstraction that
we mentioned before you would have to
build this for basically everything
right and there is no reactive thing
anymore from like you don't get the
benefit from react anymore if you if you
add everything directly and leaflet if
you look at the leaflet website there's
like a long list of plugins is there a
set of plugins that you typically use
when you know you're building a leaflet
application no somehow I'm kind of
ignorant in that sense no you're not
even the address geocoding thing I also
built is on my own there are many many
many good plugins there honestly and
what I can tell you is there are plugins
that we use at a channel or car to go
and there are plugins that I constantly
see people use together with the library
that I'm providing and these are
something like what's called an a marker
grouping tool it's mmm clustering yes
thank you marker cluster is a plugin
that is used a lot and we use this as
well so it as the name implies it
clusters the markers when you zoom out
so you don't have 10 million markers on
a map but it classes them together it's
also good for performance but also for
usability so this is something that is
used a lot and then of course everything
that creates heat maps and data
visualization also used a lot at least
from you know the circle of open-source
maintainer so open-source uses that that
I am that I'm interacting with a lot but
honestly if you are using leaflet look
at the plug-in library see what is there
before you build it yourself
try the plug-in and see if it fits your
needs because you know you don't have to
reinvent the wheel for me this might be
a bit of a sickness and it's fun to
recreate the wheel for me but of course
it's a waste of time if you have if you
have it already there yeah another thing
I'd like to ask is you know when we talk
about
displaying things on the map we were
talking about cars earlier and you're
saying you display them in the form of
markers a lot of times applications want
to show information that's associated
with those markers whether that's a
label on the map or or something else
like that how do you typically approach
that keep all all that information
grouped together and keep it updated so
I saw I saw different different
implementations you can as always the
metadata that you store with your layers
you can choose to have them its own
entity outside of the Geo JSON or you
editor GHS so the question is is the is
democra itself your source data your
your main entity that means to you do
you associate the style for a marker
with the marker or do you store the
style separate and store the idea of
democritus tile that is that is
basically an architecture question that
you have to solve a more an example that
might be that resonates maybe more with
with everyone is we have cars right so
we have cars and the cars have metadata
like license plate which tires they have
which SIM cards they use you know they
have all this a lot of data much more
than the geo data and so it's the
location of the car just the property of
the car or is everything else from the
car metadata of my of my location data
and this is a distinction you have to
decide on your own how your complete
architecture landscape and ecosystem
looks like for me I decided many times
that the location data is the source of
truth let's say and I put a lot of
metadata in that is because if if
everything the user does and everything
my API does resolves around the location
data I can just as well use that as my
main source of truth so if we go back to
styling styling in particular I would
store as metadata so you have a marker
and it it should resemble a car so I
want a different icon I maybe want the
direction if we are talking apps like
uber for example you see the direction
the car is heading so I might have a
degree so I can I know how to turn the
icon on a map I need a color and maybe I
want to display it the lane that the car
was driving you know the route so I want
to display that and all of this data I
store as metadata and if the user
changes that I change it in the metadata
of that marker that means if any team is
fetching the data from the API they have
also the information how to display it
and this is this was for me and for us
also very important to do so styling I
would definitely recommend storing this
with the geo data as metadata with
everything else like the fuel level of
the car that's that decision you have to
do on your own architecture wise and if
you wanted to make a customizable user
interface in terms of somebody chose
they wanted to see what's the speed of
the car or something like that and they
want to be able to turn it off and on
you would store what the user chose in
the same place what what the user chose
in the sense of okay I want to see the
fuel level I want to see the the license
right if they want to be able to turn it
on and on so that that is a big use case
I think that's the use case for everyone
that displays markers let's let's use
Tesla superchargers for example you have
the location of the supercharger and and
if you click on one you have the address
the exact location how many are there
how many are currently free blah blah
all of all of this data like is you can
you can you eat there other restrooms
etc so
Tesla they don't give you the data as
you Jason they give you a collection of
superchargers basically an array with
objects and just the location of the
supercharger is a geo Jason that means
you have a big collection of Jason data
and a subset property of each entry is a
GU Jason that is also how we do it at
car to go and and channel so yeah geo
jason is just a part of a bigger data
set but in geo man for example i reverse
that I use GU Jason as the main source
and have basically most of the data as
metadata inside the geo Jason it doesn't
make a big difference to anyone it's
just a preference of how you how you
manage your data and again what is your
main entity is your entity a car that
has a location property or is your main
entity a marker and a cop being a car is
just a property of that marker could
also be a plane or abuser so because I
build an application where everything
revolves around location data I chose
the location is the is my main entity
and that is the geo Jason and the fact
that it's a car it's just a metadata a
property of it with a specific icon
basically like you know my application
doesn't care if it's a plane or a car at
the end of the day I guess another thing
I'd like to ask about is when people use
Maps a lot of times they're on their
phones as well as just being on the
desktop what's your approach or what are
things to watch out for when building a
site that needs to work on both desktop
very tricky very tricky so two things if
you just want to display it so again the
use case of you have your you location
of a business or something that you
would like to display that is no problem
at all leaflet is very mobile friendly
and if you just display the marker the
user can zoom in and out construes can
easily scroll through so if your thumb
goes on the map and you scroll you might
have seen this with Google Maps right in
Google Maps to zoom or to move the map
you need to use two fingers they do that
so you can easily scroll through the
website without you know that your
scrolling is interrupted by you're
moving the map instead so this kind of
functionality to to make it
mobile-friendly is there in all of these
libraries so this is an easy thing you
don't have to do anything it just works
out of the box but if you create more
advanced interactions with a map like
for example a user should be able to
draw a polygon then it gets more
trickier and geo man and also my library
leaflet human they both work on mobile I
think that is also one reason why it's
getting quite popular because
from my research it's the only drawing
tool that works on mobile but if you use
your thumb it gets an India small screen
it gets less precise your drawings so I
have features like pinning that means if
you click near a different marker it
just snaps them together so it assumes
you want to have you want to place them
on top of each other that's a really
cool use cases specially on desktop
where you can easily move to markers but
on mobile it's not that easy so I
personally think it's possible but it's
it's not a good way to do that except
for let's say you have an iPad pro with
a pen then it's really cool then I was
really impressed when I used my library
for the first time on an iPad pro with a
pen because then you can draw really
precisely it's a lot of fun it's easy to
do that's really cool so if you have
advanced interactions with mobile then
you will get into situations with click
click events and stuff like this where
it gets maybe a little bit more tricky
and use cases where you hover the mouse
over the map and you display things or
you give the user a hint of what will
happen when they click you can't do this
on mobile so it's a it's a much it's
it's basically different experience and
in a sense a limited functionality if we
are talking about drawing so this you
should keep in mind if it's strictly
about displaying data you will not have
a problem mm-hmm and in terms of the I
guess the UI like it may need to be
significantly different right between
desktop and
mobile do you effectively kind of hide a
lot of UI elements are kind of build to
you know components depending on what
size the viewport is yeah of course so
in German I use the disciple for example
right if you display it on mobile you
don't see the map anymore and it's just
a lot of data so the more data you show
and a more meta data you want to display
the trickier it gets how to display this
on mobile and
the map should be front and center
especially on a on a tool that revolves
around that so that means if you opened
human io on your on your phone you only
see the map and you have a small icon on
top that that moves in the sidebar for
example it's still not perfect I think
it's a limited use case also my
particular app to use this on mobile but
of course you have the same problem with
any website that displays a lot of data
you have to hide some you might have to
basically also we do some data like some
data you just don't need on mobile you
will reduce maybe the table columns you
know stuff like this to make to make it
as easy as possible for the user on
mobile and they can still open a desktop
view if they want to on mobile but it's
such a limited use case I think that
as long as it looks good and it has the
basic information I think everyone is
fine if you go into it Advanced Mode
then a desktop might be or a tablet
might be the way to go for a user yeah
we've been talking about geo man and
you've mentioned that you have a leaflet
plugin called geo man leaflet can you
kind of go into a little bit about what
geo man is and why you decided to create
your manly yeah yeah sure so human just
so you know it's not a superhero or
something like this it it derived from
geo management and I just noticed later
that it sounds like some sort of
superhero
anyway I so I have a quite let's say
experience now in solving this for
companies and seeing the problems inside
companies and this not only in the
mobility space this ranges to to
communication providers to again
construction sites and logistics
companies and everyone that has
geospatial data and they mostly have two
there are two categories I would say
that I'm trying to help one is they have
their own application they have their
own team that works on this or multiple
teams and they use open-source products
or paid products and they use they need
more functionality so they probably use
my open-source library if they use
leaflet for creating data and
the open source library basically helps
you create and edit this kind of data so
you need to create a polygon you can
create this of course by just providing
the the coordinates if you notice but if
you have a user and he needs to for
example create a polygon around a
building or block or a city or whatever
my library is there to help them just
you know easily create these polygons on
the map they can create markers circles
rectangles whatever it is they can also
edit this edit each specific vertex add
vertexes in between they can move the
entire shape they can cut holes and
polygons they can of course remove the
polygons so all of these drawing and
editing features are there and one
product I'm currently thinking about I'm
just collecting feedback I've not build
it yet is approver of that that has even
more advanced drawing and editing
features something like some companies
need need to have polygons that are
adjacent to each other and cover a
complete area like a city and they have
maybe 100 or 200 polygons that make up
the city so let's think of it like sales
territories or something like this and
there there should not be an overlap or
a hole between these polygons so they
need to stick together now they can do
this already with the open source
libraries and providing but if they want
to change the shape of one polygon they
would have to change all of the adjacent
polygons as well which is quite a lot of
work and I could build a tool for
example where you just draw a new border
and it automatically calculates the new
size of each of those polygons and
adapts that because you basically tell
them hey I don't want any overlap and I
don't want any hole in it and these are
such advanced niche drawing tools that
require weeks and months of work to
build that I want to wait if people or
if companies need this and I'm thinking
about providing basically a pro version
of the open source library so that means
I have two open source library that I
could constantly maintain for basic
drawing and editing needs I wouldn't say
it's basic it's quite advanced already
then we have really advanced tools where
I think a pro version of the library
would be helpful for some companies and
then we have the second bucket of
companies that don't build it on their
own application they just want a way to
easily have a service like MailChimp for
example instead of managing email they
want to manage tree of special data so
they want a service where they can
create data where it can put data into
an API and where all the teams and
clients and apps can fetch the data
again and this is where the SAS
applications comes in and it's called
geo man basically and there you have a
studio where you have your map or you
can create multiple Maps like projects
and then you create for example one map
that displays your
supercharger network you have one map
that displays your sales territories or
your parking spots you can create one
map that displays Airlines routes
whatever it is whatever your data is and
for me the powerful thing that would
solve a lot of problems inside companies
is you can draw this any user can draw
us it can be a working student that
creates parking spots for example in a
city then you have your developers that
not only consume the data but they can
write the data through the API and it's
updated everywhere on every consumer and
you can attach the metadata to it to put
everything in so to summarize there's
geo man the application which is where
somebody can draw shapes or add data
probably import data from something like
say a CSV or an API or something like
that and then if you had an application
that wanted to consume the data geo man
itself has an API for people to get data
back out exactly and then geo men
leaflet is the leaflet plug-in that you
built and use within the Geo Man
application exactly and it's it's open
source for anyone that wants to build
basically their own application two
minutes to you data and
yeah so I got asked a lot for example
why do I open sources because it's it
seems like it's one of the best plugins
out there like I don't want to say
anything falls here I'm not sure about
that but users tell me they switch to it
for example from other libraries and I
also haven't seen other libraries that
provide the same functionality so it's
one of the more advanced ones and people
ask me why do I open sources why it's
not why is it not part of the German
suite that makes it a reason for people
to use and the reason is simply that I
know that German will not cover all use
cases that are out there people need
very specific needs and GU data and I
like open source I love contributing to
it I love the interaction with the
community and it's I think it's a great
open source product i personally benefit
a lot from open sources whether
specifically with leaflet and I thought
human as a platform can be a way for me
to earn money and invest more time into
the open source product that I can then
give back again you know what I mean so
open source I've maintained this library
for four years now I have not earned a
single euro with it and it costs a lot
of time and I feel bad if I don't
maintain it for a month or something
but if if the platform is successful
then I have more time to develop it
right there is a like a it serves
multiple purposes not only for me
personally but also I can maintain the
library much better at much more
features for anyone that wants to build
their own own application with the open
source tools very cool so hopefully at
some point you'll get to spend more time
in your day job working on geo men and
working on geo manly Flynn would love to
yeah cool to start wrapping for people
who are learning leaflet are there
common mistakes you see people make or
suggestions you have for people who are
learning leaflet now yeah so if you if
you go through the docs and and use you
know the standard Stack Overflow to
instead that we all use every day you
will get quite far what I see a lot
especially if you use frameworks and
beginners with leaflet they struggle
sometimes to make this mental
distinction between these two universes
these two ecosystems so if you use a
reactive framework like react view
angular just know that leaflet itself is
not it's not part of that you you create
you interact with the Dom directly as
mentioned before so don't expect like
this reactivity this you just provided
something and everything you know
changes on the map this is something
where I see a lot of questions happening
then on the other hand the business side
so think of the thing of leaflet and
mapping like they provides you the tools
to display a map and data on top of it
but the business logic behind it
how do you store it in what data format
are I want a tile to be red if it's
overlapping something else this kind of
stuff you have to build yourself or use
a plugin for it like it it won't create
business logic for you it's basically
the dumb way of rendering data not that
dumb but I hope you get what I mean
right you have business logic that is
specific to you and you have to build
this yourself so the library will not do
this out of the box for you so I see
these questions a lot also under open
source repository but people just expect
expect it to do things but they can
easily do this in three lines of codes
they just haven't wrapped the head
around yet what exactly is leaflet doing
for you and what not so if you have any
kind of business logic this should
happen when this course this is
something you you have to build yourself
and it's honestly quite easy but if you
have any questions I'm happy to help not
only for my open source library I'm on
Twitter and everywhere so I'm happy to
help out cool all right there any
specific projects that people should
look at if they're trying to learn how
an application should be laid out in
leaflet so there are multiple demo
projects for basically all the plugins
they're demo projects and also for
leaflet itself you can look at human
that IO which is quite
let's say more advanced use case I would
say how you yeah what map functionality
you can add to a map and
everything from uber of course is very
advanced and especially in data
visualization they have amazing tools
and it's all open source also so if you
use at the demo pages if you look at the
demo pages from uber and from map box
you will get a sense of where it can go
and then I would personally just look
into the doll and and see what they do
and how they do it maybe they have an
open source repository where I can take
a look and also for example if you want
to write your own plugin with leaflet
look at the look at the open source code
that's how I started like I had no idea
how to create a plug-in for leaflet or
how to manage to use special data like I
just didn't know all I had was I needed
functionality that no plugin had so I
lived a draw was back then the only one
I basically scanned their code looked
how they do it try to recreate it and
then build my own architecture with it
but it was very similar in the beginning
the code so just look that's what open
source is therefore look into the code
learn from that clone it adapt it and
grow from there how about in terms of
like a full application like you're
mentioning to look at say gee oh man dot
IO but geuman itself is not actually
open source is it no okay yeah so I'm
not sure where to look there
what I do sometimes okay you have stuff
like geo json dot io it's a small
utility to to edit you Jace and I've
built the same on on GM and IO but yeah
it's a different one from map box and
this is open source it's a small
application that yeah that you can take
a look at what I can also recommend is
if you for example you want to create a
leaflet map and you don't know how the
demos are not enough for you you want to
see some real use cases with react for
example what I do is I used two advanced
search functionality on github so I look
at who uses leaflet and who uses react
and maybe I search for the inception
code from leaflet and filter by it and
then you find a lot of applications that
basically use it like this and then I
scan around and try to find someone that
uses the same stack as me and how they
do it and this gives me a lot of
inspiration yeah that's a great tip not
just for leaflet but for anytime you're
trying to learn a new library yeah it's
really helpful yeah the github search
functionality is underrated I think in
that sense cool well before we finish up
is there anything that you think we
should have mentioned or should have
talked about I think we had a quite
awesome overview i've there is not not
much to mention if you are into into
geospatial data or if you have to prop
to solve the problem for your company or
your client or whatever I think it's
it's quite the interesting field it's
it's quite a niche also but yeah the
user experience is it's amazing and you
have such a big impact if you if you
build something nice on top of maps and
of course it's a field that is very very
future proof it doesn't matter if we're
talking drones autonomous vehicles say
it's like everything in the mobility
sector specifically but everything
around us needs more and more location
data because everything is connected and
I think it's a field where you as a
developer if you have these skills I was
very good equipped for the future so
don't hesitate to get into it and code a
bit around it I don't think you will
regret it call and for people who want
to follow you or see what's going on
with Geo man where should they go so I'm
on too many platforms I say but I'm
active very active on twitter my handle
is tweets of sumit there I'm the most
active so if there is anything you would
like to ask or if you want to follow me
and you know see where geuman is going
the open-source library or also even how
to create the business I cannot let an
expert in it I just share my journey I
will share everything on on Twitter and
if I have a for example a YouTube video
or even a guest appearance on a podcast
like this one and I will share
everything there so I think that is the
that is the best way and of course you
can go to my website which is home dot
sh about mr. John what realm for room of
all not SH Esther is my personal website
where I also post occasional updates
here in there very cool well thank you
so much for talking to me today see me
thanks for having me Jeremy was nice
talking to you
thanks for listening to se Radio an
educational program brought to you by
Triple E software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at SE - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com
[Music]
you can also email us at team @ SC -
radio net this and all other episodes of
se Radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license 2.5 thanks for listening
[Music]